Guide to the Marie Trommer Collection 1909-1970 PR 437
New-York Historical Society
Marie Trommer collection
1909-1970
New-York Historical Society
Trommer, Marie, 1895-1971
PR 437
7 Linear feet in 6 record cartons and 1 flat box
The collection consists primarily of the artwork and writing of Marie Trommer (1895-1971), a Ukrainian-born American artist, art critic, poet, and journalist.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format.
Biographical / Historical
Marie Trommer (1895-1971) was a Ukrainian-born artist, art critic, poet, and journalist. Trommer was born in Kremenchoug, Ukraine on September 29, 1895 to Bernard and Betha (Yedlin) Trembitsky. The family immigrated to the United States in 1905, settling in Brooklyn; Marie was then known as Mary Trembitsky. After graduating from Cooper Union Art School in 1914, she changed her name to Marie Trommer and established herself as an artist and art critic in New York City. A staff member of the Jewish Tribune, Trommer contributed to many other American Jewish publications, including the Jewish Daily News and the Boston Jewish Advocate. In addition, Trommer edited the American-Russian Review, and was known for her translations of Russian and Ukrainian literature into English, as well as translations of American and British poetry into Russian.
Marie Trommer's artwork was first exhibited at the Society of Independent Artists in 1924. Her work was shown consistently over the following 30 years, with exhibitions at the American Museum of Natural History and the Grant Galleries, among others. Trommer specialized in landscapes and figures, working primarily in oils, pen and ink, and watercolors. She also worked with textiles, especially embroidery, creating many colorful mixed media pieces that incorporate sequins, buttons, beads, metallic thread, and more.
Marie Trommer died in New York City on February 6, 1971.
Source: Botnick, Annette Muffs. "Marie Trommer." Shalvi/Hyman Encyclopedia of Jewish Women. 31 December 1999. Jewish Women's Archive. (Viewed on March 15, 2022) https://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/trommer-marie.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
No information is available at this time.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of the artwork and writing of Marie Trommer (1895-1971). Included are more than 500 pages of Trommer's translations of Russian, Ukrainian, and Yiddish works into English; about 150 poems by Trommer, many of which she also illustrated; some 500 sketches, most done with pen and ink on scrap paper; about 300 watercolor views of New York City, most of which include date, location, and subject on the verso; and over 100 pieces of mixed media textile art that incorporates embroidery, sequins, buttons, beads, metallic thread, and more. These textile art pieces include small chapbooks with embellished covers and handmade bookplates.
The collection also contains a small number of personal papers; some photographic negatives of New York City scenes; and bits of ephemera that Trommer collected. Most of this ephemera is related to New York City and State political candidates and campaigns. However, there are also flyers for demonstrations and public events, advertisements for astrologers and healers, as well as some greeting cards and calendars. Of special interest is a collection of greeting cards for Jewish holidays, many written in Hebrew. These cards were part of an album that Marie Trommer donated to the New-York Historical Society in 1963, which was found with this collection.
Jewish women artists; Jewish women authors; Women journalists -- United States.; Ephemera.; Literature--Translations; Poems; Political pins; Political posters; Sketches.; Textile crafts; Watercolors (paintings)
- Art: Early Work, 1909-1914 (Offsite-box 7)
  Scope and Contents
  4 paintings, 12 sketches from Trommer's art school years. Some are signed "Mary Trembitsky." Very fragile.
- Art: Sketches, 1909-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-5)
  Approximately 500 sketches, most pen and ink on scrap paper.
- Art: Textile crafts (1 of 4), 1952-1970 (Offsite-box 3)
  Mixed media textile pieces.
- Art: Textile crafts (2 of 4), 1952-1970 (Offsite-box 4)
- Art: Textile crafts (3 of 4), 1952-1970 (Offsite-box 5)
- Art: Textile crafts (4 of 4), 1952-1970 (Offsite-box 6)
- Art: Watercolors, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-12)
  There are approximately 300 watercolors, mostly views of all five boroughs of New York City, with location, description, and date on the verso.
- Ephemera: General, 1900-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-14)
  Subjects include:
  the American flag
  astrology and prognostication
  calendars printed by the Charles C. Morchand Company, 1941-1968
  Jewish/Hebrew cards from an album donated to N-YHS by Marie Trommer in 1963
  other holiday cards
  demonstrations and protests
  cultural events
  health topics
  television and movies
  miscellaneous.
- Ephemera: Objects, undated (Offsite-box 7)
  Consists of spoons; beads; samplers (not embroidered by Marie Trommer); toothbrush holder; letter opener. Includes notes about some of the items.
- Ephemera: Political, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15-19)
  Includes flyers, pins, stickers and pamphlets related to political campaigns, mainly from elections in New York City and New York State.
- Personal Papers, 1934-1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  American-Russian Review April-May 1937; Society for Jewish Culture publication, circa 1926; three letters; three copy photographs from the New-York Historical Society; two clippings; and a handwritten list of 12 operas that Marie and her family attended.
- Photographic Negatives, 1940-1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  Images of New York City, including views of Coney Island, Radio City Music Hall, Rockefeller Center, and the 1968 "Garbage Strike."
- Poems, 1954-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13-14)
  About 150 poems written by Marie Trommer, many of which are handwritten and/or illustrated.
- Translations, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15-19)
  Russian, Ukrainian, and Yiddish works translated into English by Marie Trommer.